<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Urban Scientist</title>
    <description>The Urbanist Scientist&#39;s guide to the curiosities of Mathematic&#39;s, Machines and Economic&#39;s.</description>
    <link>/</link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 21:57:37 -0600</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 21:57:37 -0600</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Web Scraper to gather Historical Powerball Lottery Data</title>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the previous blog post, we explored the mathematical underpinnings behind the Powerball lottery. We learned that using enumerative combinatorics, we can calculate the number of possible combinations that exist within any given Powerball drawing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within this article, we will learn how to build a web scraper using Python that gathers historical winning Powerball Number combinations. &lt;!--more--&gt; Once we have gathered the scraped information, we will learn how to clean it and convert it into it usable Pandas DataFrame. &lt;label for=&quot;One&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;One&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;I will be using Python 3.7 for this project. Access the associated &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Jupyter Notebook&lt;/a&gt; for the project here. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brief-web-scraping-overview&quot;&gt;Brief Web Scraping Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Web scraper is a program that uses the hypertext transfer protocol to request information from websites, and then saves that information for some purpose. A web scraper behaves similar to an API, in that it can be run to consistently return desired information from a website. However, more often than not the websites that house the information that we are interested in, are not robust enough to have a need to provide an API. With this it forces us to be clever as to how we extract information that we want from the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of a rudimentary web scraper is to copy and paste the information that we’re looking for, from the site, into a program like Google Sheets or Microsoft Excel. Beyond being tedious and time intensive, there is another reason why copying and pasting is not an optimal web scraping process. Say for instance the information that is being scraped changes periodically. The individual who is doing the copying and pasting would have to iteratively go back and copy and paste the new information each time a change occurred. In this article we will build and implement a web scraper using Python. It will allow us to iteratively and consistently collect the information that we’re looking for each time we use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;legality-of-web-scrapers&quot;&gt;Legality of Web Scrapers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this point here in the article I do want to say that there is a matter of legality associated with web scrapers. One, the way that web scrapers are built they can iteratively make thousands of HTTP GET requests from sites in a very short amount time. This when done improperly can send large unexpected traffic loads to server hosting website potentially cause the site to go down. Two, if the site explicitly states within their terms of service (ToS) or within their prohibited operations page, that automated data collection is not allowed, then don’t do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great way to check the sites rules on web scraping is to look for a page called robots.txt. On most sites this file denotes what is and is not allowed for web scrapers (i.e. robots) to crawl/scrape. This article we will be using the Wisconsin lottery’s website to collect historical Powerball winning ticket combinations. Going to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wilottery.com/robots.txt&quot;&gt;Wisconson Lottery’s Robots.txt File&lt;/a&gt;, we see that there are only two disallowed processes for web scrapers. Luckily, we will be scraping neither of these sections of the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-web-scrapers-work&quot;&gt;How Web Scrapers Work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three primary components of any web scraper. The first component of any web scraper gives it the ability to parse the HTML of a given website. The second component searches over the HTML and gathers the information of interest. Within our web scraper we will define a function called &lt;em&gt;parse_and_gather()&lt;/em&gt;  that does both of these processes automatically for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the web scraper has parsed the HTML and gathered the pertinent information, it is up to the developer to decide what the most applicable format to convert the data to. Thus, the final component have any web scraper formats together data into the appropriate format. In our case, we will write another function called &lt;em&gt;build_dataframe()&lt;/em&gt;, that takes the gathered information and converts it into a Pandas DataFrame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;import-the-necessary-packages&quot;&gt;Import the Necessary Packages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;pandas&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;requests&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;lxml.html&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;as&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;lh&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pandas.pydata.org&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pandas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Pandas is an Open-Source Project and a python library that helps python users work with multidimensional data, or panel data in a computational form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.python-requests.org/en/master/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Requests&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - Requests is a python library that makes using the Hypertext Transfer Protocol via python a simple to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lxml.de&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lxml&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; - LXML is a python library that allow python users a way to computationally interact with HTML or XML elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;build-a-header-dictionary&quot;&gt;Build a Header dictionary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After importing the necessary Python libraries, let us begin to discuss the hypertext transfer protocol (HTTP) at a little more depth. There’re two primary actors within HTTP process. There is the client, who requests information from the server. And then there is the server which responds to the client by sending resources like HTML files and other content. HTTP was built to facilitate and set standardized guidelines to this request and response process between a client and the server. Within a client request to a server there are typically three primary components that make up a request message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first part you have the request line otherwise known as the client request method. This request method tells the server explicitly the information that the client is requesting to be served. They are several different kinds of request methods the client can make to a server, these include GET, POST, DELETE, TRACE, CONNECT, OPTIONS, PUT, and HEAD requests.The second part of the request message we call HTTP header fields which are used to relay specific information about the client to the server.The final component is an optional message that can be sent to the specific server from the client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When building a web scraper, you must have the first component of a client request message to gather the information from the server. The two most common request methods that we use within our web scrapers are the GET and POST methods. GET method allows us to request a specific set of information from the server, whereas the POST method allows us to send a specific set of information to server. Within our web scraper we will use an GET method to request the relevant Powerball data from the Wisconsin lottery website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though not a necessity, it is always good practice to include the second component of the client request method within your web scraper. Again, remember that the second component of the request is the HTTP header. The reason why this is so crucial is because it allows the server to verify that the client requesting information is a valid client. HTTP request headers are also helpful in what’s known as content negotiation, where clients specify to the server the specific type of content that they’re requesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our specific case we will use a python dictionary named headers to define our HTTP request headers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;headers&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;	&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;accept&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;text/html,application/xhtml+xml,application/xml;q=0.9,image/webp,*/*;q=0.8&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;accept-encoding&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;gzip, deflate, sdch, br&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;accept-language&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;en-GB,en-US;q=0.8,en;q=0.6&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;upgrade-insecure-requests&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;1&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;user-agent&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Mozilla/5.0 (X11; Linux x86_64) Chrome/51.0.2704.79 Safari/537.36&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Cache-Control&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;no-cache&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Connection&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;keep-alive&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have an &lt;em&gt;accept&lt;/em&gt; request field that tells the server the types of media that are acceptable to send back to us from the GET request. Here we define several different variants of HTML or XML that is appropriate to send it back. The addition of a lowercase ‘q’ in any request field indicates to the server something called the relative quality factor. This parameter is a range from [0-1] and defines to the relative degree of preference for each content type. If there is no q parameter defined, the entry is defaulted to a q parameter of 1. Further breaking down our accept request field, we see that the entries &lt;em&gt;’text/html’&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;’application/xhtml+xml’&lt;/em&gt; do not have a q parameter, but the final entries &lt;em&gt;’application/xml;q=0.9’&lt;/em&gt; and ,&lt;em&gt;’asterisk /asterisk’=0.8’&lt;/em&gt; both do. This means that we are telling the server that we prefer the first to entries as they default to 1, and we prefer the final two entries at 90% and 80% respectively.&lt;label for=&quot;One&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;One&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;The ‘asterisk /asterisk’ requests from the server to use all other forms of the entry. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next request field is the &lt;em&gt;accept-encoding&lt;/em&gt; field, which defines the type of content compression that is acceptable for the server to send back to us. In our case, this request field might be slightly redundant, because the information or requesting should needs no compression. Yet, rather than taking it out I thought I’d leave it in for you to see. After we define the acceptable compression, we then define the acceptable language, if applicable, for the server to send back information in. Here we denote this field as the &lt;em&gt;accept-language&lt;/em&gt; field. We tell the server to send the information back to us in English (United States or British).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;build-the-parse--gather-function&quot;&gt;Build the Parse &amp;amp; Gather Function&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;parse_and_gather&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;sd&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&amp;#39;This function makes the GET request &amp;amp; collects the data&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#HTTP GET Call Setup&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;url&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;https://www.wilottery.com/lottogames/powerballhistoryOD.aspx&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;response&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;url&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;headers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;headers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;lh&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;fromstring&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;response&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;table_elements&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;xpath&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;//tr&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Define the Column Headers for the 5 Empty Column Headers&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num_list&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Num_1&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Num_2&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Num_3&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Num_4&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Num_5&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Fill in the Column Headers&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;col_header&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;text_content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;table_elements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;col&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,[]]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;col_header&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Fill in the middle 5 empty column headers with num_list&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num_list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;j&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;col&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;][&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;num_list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Beacause the first row is the headers, the data is stored on the second row onwards&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;j&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;table_elements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;table_elements&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;j&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# If the table has more than the 8 Columns on the WI Lottery Site&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;!=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;break&lt;/span&gt;

        &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Convert the elements into integers and save them to col lists.     &lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;iterchildren&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;text_content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;try&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;except&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
                    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;pass&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;col&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;][&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;append&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;col&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;build-the-formatting-function&quot;&gt;Build the Formatting Function&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;build_dataframe&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;sd&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&amp;#39; This function creates a Pandas DataFrame from the data&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Call the Gather Data Function&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;col&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;parse_and_gather&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Convert to a Dictionary&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;header&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;column&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;header&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;column&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;col&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Create a DataFrame&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DataFrame&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;from_dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Dict&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Set the Date Column as the index&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;set_index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Draw Date&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;inplace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Convert the Index to a Pandas DatetimeIndex&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;to_datetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;index&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Selects all Non-Digits&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digits&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;r&amp;quot;\D+&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Selects all spaces&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;spaces&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;r&amp;quot;\s+&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Splits the powerplay column into just the integer values&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Power Play_Clean&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Power Play&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;astype&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;split&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;spaces&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;split&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;digits&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;str&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Drop the old Powerplay column&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;drop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Power Play&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;axis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;inplace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Add a new Powerplay column that contains the cleaned information&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Power Play&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pd&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;to_numeric&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Power Play_Clean&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;errors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;coerce&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;downcast&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;integer&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#Drop the Cleaning Column&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;drop&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;Power Play_Clean&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;axis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;inplace&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;df&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;view-output&quot;&gt;View Output&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jan 2019 15:46:04 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/19/Data-Science-on-the-Powerball-blog</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/19/Data-Science-on-the-Powerball-blog</guid>
        
        
        <category>machines</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Mathematical Understanding of the Powerball Lottery</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The popular Powerball lottery offered in the United States has in the past years, evolved to accommodate larger payouts due to several iterative adjustments in the game’s structure. The most recent adjustment was set in place for the drawing which occurred on October 7th, 2015. This probabilistic alteration opened the opportunity for players to potentially win payouts in excess of $1 billion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post is the first in a series and seeks to understand how to calculate and comprehend the underlying probabilities associated with the Powerball lottery game. &lt;!--more--&gt; If you prefer to computationally walk through the blog post, I will place code snippets within this article for you to run on your own &lt;label for=&quot;One&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;One&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;I will be using Python 3.7 for this project. Access the associated &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/UrbanScientist/1_Mathematical_Understanding_of_Powerball&quot;&gt;Jupyter Notebook&lt;/a&gt; for the project here. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;brief-history-of-the-powerball-lottery-game&quot;&gt;Brief History of the Powerball Lottery Game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Formed through a collaborative effort between the Multi-State Lottery Association (a nonprofit organization), and an agreement with the other US lotteries, the Powerball came into fruition. As mentioned in the name of the organization that set it up, the Powerball lottery is a Multi-State lottery game offered for to players across 44 States in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the efforts of the Multi-State Lottery Association, the first Powerball drawing was held in 1992. Unlike the other lottery game structures of the time, the Powerball became the first lottery game to use two different pools of balls from which the winning numbers were selected from. This was especially important for the Multi-State Lottery Association, because this two-pool system offered more variation in the numbers for players to select from, implicitly leading to high jackpot odds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-game-structure&quot;&gt;The Game Structure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who are not familiar with how to play the Powerball lottery, the game structure is very simple. There is one player who chooses two sets of numbers from two different pools. One can think of a pool as consisting of a range from 1 to &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt;, where the range implies that for every integer &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; within it is greater than or equal to 1, and less than or equal to &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt; Pool = {[1,N] \implies \{ x \in \mathbb{Z} :  1  \leq  x  \leq  N\}}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The players can select their two different sets of numbers by using the “Quick Pick” option, which allows a machine to choose random values for their ticket, or the players can manually create their own selection matrix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;powerball-ticket-combinations&quot;&gt;Powerball Ticket Combinations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first pool, or the white balls in the Powerball, &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; = 69 making the range of possible selections a range from 1 to 69. The player must select five different numbers from the first pool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt; First Pool = {[1,69] \implies \{ x \in \mathbb{Z} :  1  \leq  x  \leq  69\}}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These five numbers, regardless of their order, must match the five numbers drawn from the &lt;em&gt;FirstPool&lt;/em&gt; by the lottery in order for a chance to win the entire Jackpot. In the game play, when the first number is drawn it has a 1 in 69 possibility of matching a ball drawn in the lottery, this leads to the second number being drawn from a pool of 68 numbers, or a 1 in 68 possibility of matching a ball in the lottery. This type of combination is considered a &lt;em&gt;combination without replacement&lt;/em&gt;. When continuing this logic forward across all the five numbers necessary we arrive at, (1  in  69 x 68 x 67 x 66 x 65) possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This expression can be mathematically articulated using enumerative combinatorics. Combinatorics broadly is a branch of mathematics whose primary concern is the utilization of certain methodological processes as a means to count, and to extrapolate results from a finite set. When narrowing in on enumerative combinatorics we use the twelvefold way, a framework for counting permutations&lt;label for=&quot;Two&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;Two&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Permutation&lt;/em&gt;: An ordinal or sequential arrangement of the components of a set. &lt;/span&gt;, combinations &lt;label for=&quot;Three&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;Three&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Combination&lt;/em&gt;: The arrangement of a set without reference to the order of the components. &lt;/span&gt; and partitions. We will use this use this to define the range of possible combinations in the Powerball lottery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can think of the range of possible numbers to be drawn as an immutable set &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; of integers whose bounds are defined in the aforementioned &lt;em&gt;FirstPool&lt;/em&gt; definition. A k-combination is a finite portion of set &lt;em&gt;S&lt;/em&gt; with &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; number of distinct elements. If the range of the set is known, &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; is the inclusive maximum element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Powerball’s &lt;em&gt;FirstPool&lt;/em&gt; we can define &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; as equal to 69, and &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; as equal to 5. I will acknowledge that factorials are computationally slow, but here we will use them for simple explanation’s sake. Using previously defined &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; within equation below we will arrive at the total number of combinations including permutations within the Powerball lottery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt; \frac{n!}{(n-k)!} &lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The computational expression of the binomial coefficient calculation expresses the optionality to include or exclude permutations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nn&quot;&gt;scipy.special&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kn&quot;&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;factorial&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;binomial_coefficient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;perm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;False&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;sd&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&amp;#39;Calculates the Binomial Coefficient (n choose k)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;sd&quot;&gt;    Keyword Arguments:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sd&quot;&gt;    n = denotes the maximum value in a range from (1,n)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sd&quot;&gt;    k = denotes the number of values selected from the n range&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sd&quot;&gt;    perm = denotes whether permutations are included&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sd&quot;&gt;    &amp;#39;&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;perm&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;binomial_coefficient&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;round&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;factorial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;factorial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;binomial_coefficient&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;round&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;factorial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;factorial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;factorial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;binomial_coefficient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this function we can calculate that number of possible combinations and permutations in the &lt;em&gt;FirstPool&lt;/em&gt; of the Powerball Lottery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;binomial_coefficient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;69&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;perm&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;bp&quot;&gt;True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads to &lt;strong&gt;1,348,621,560 combinations and permutations&lt;/strong&gt;. Restating once more, that in order to win a prize from the Powerball lottery the order of your selection of numbers is irrelevant, and thus we can eliminate the permutations. We eliminate the permutations by multiplying the denominator by &lt;em&gt;k!&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;label for=&quot;Five&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;Five&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;This is accomplished by default with the perm parameter of the binomial_coefficient function. &lt;/span&gt;  We do this because given any set of &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; numbers there are &lt;em&gt;k!&lt;/em&gt; number of ways that &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; could have been drawn. Thus, when we divide the 1,348,621,560 by &lt;em&gt;k!&lt;/em&gt; we eliminate the effect of the permutations. &lt;label for=&quot;Four&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;Four&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;This factorial expression of the k-combinatorial calculation in &lt;em&gt;Eq.2&lt;/em&gt; is also equivalent to the binomial coefficient. Throughout the remainder of this article we will syntactically use the binomial coefficient notation  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;  \frac{n!}{k!(n-k)!} = \binom{n}{k}  &lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using this function we can calculate that number of possible combinations in the &lt;em&gt;FirstPool&lt;/em&gt; of the Powerball Lottery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;binomial_coefficient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;69&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads to &lt;strong&gt;11,238,513 combinations&lt;/strong&gt; in the Powerball lottery’s first five numbers. The binomial coefficient can also be thought of as the collection of probabilities. When thinking about the Powerball, the probabilities associated with the first number would be 5 out of 69, the next being 4 out of 68, and so on until it renders the equation below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;{n \choose k}={69 \choose 5}={69 \over 5}* {68 \over 4} * {67 \over 3} * {66 \over 2} * {65 \over 1}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When considering the Powerball, simply calculating the number of combinations across the first pool is not enough. There is a second pool where a red ball is drawn from. &lt;label for=&quot;Five&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;Five&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;The red ball is the &lt;strong&gt;Powerball&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/span&gt; The number of balls in the second pool is 26, making &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; = 26 with the range of possible selections being a range from 1 to 26. The player must select just one number from the second pool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt; Second Pool = {[1,26] \implies \{ x \in \mathbb{Z} :  1  \leq  x  \leq  26\}}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to calculate the number of combinations including the second pool we modify the aforementioned probabilistic equation slightly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;{n \choose k}={69 \choose 5}={69 \over 5}* {68 \over 4} * {67 \over 3} * {66 \over 2} * {65 \over 1} * {26 \over 1}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this addition of the second pool the number of combinations increases to &lt;strong&gt;292,201,338&lt;/strong&gt; possible combinations. We can refer to the span of all of the different combinations as the &lt;em&gt;number space&lt;/em&gt;. The ratio of the number of the combinations in play for one drawing relative to the number space is denoted as the &lt;em&gt;coverage&lt;/em&gt; in a lottery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-odds-of-winning&quot;&gt;The Odds of Winning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having discussed how to calculate the possible combinations in the Powerball, let us end by discussing the odds of winning. For now let us just consider the five white balls in the &lt;em&gt;Firstpool&lt;/em&gt;, and we will discuss the inclusion of the Powerball momentarily. We start with the total number of combinations that are possible if all of the five white balls are selected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;{\binom{69}{5}} = 11,238,513 different combinations&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, we will define an expression that describes the odds of choosing &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; winning numbers out of the 5 possible winning white balls of the Powerball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;{5 \choose n}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this expression we can also think about the inverse of the odds of choosing &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; odds. They would imply that there are 5-n chances to choose a loosing number from the 69-k, or 64 losing numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;{69-k \choose 5-n} = {64 \choose 5-n}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking both the odds of choosing &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; winning numbers multiplied by the odds of choosing &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; loosing numbers, divided by the odds of choosing all of the winning numbers, we arrive at the odds of choosing &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; correct numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;{5 \choose n}{64 \choose 5-n}\over {69 \choose 5}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our example it is used where &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; is the number of balls in a single pool, &lt;em&gt;K&lt;/em&gt; is the number of balls in a selection from a single pool, and &lt;em&gt;B&lt;/em&gt; is the number of matching balls on a single draw.&lt;label for=&quot;Six&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;Six&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;The generalized equation is known as the hypergeometric distribution. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;{K \choose B}{N-K \choose K-B} \over {N \choose K}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This equation would work perfectly except for one final caveat. That being that the Powerball Lottery has two pools which balls are selected from. Just as we did before, the rectification of the equation to accommodate two pools is not difficult. Having only one ball selected from the pool, we can take the probability of it getting selected, multiplied across the numerator of the hypergeometric distribution. With this modification it alters the equation to allow for the selection of 1 ball out of pool &lt;em&gt;P&lt;/em&gt;, along with the other aforementioned variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;{1 \over P}{K \choose B}{N-K \choose K-B} \over {N \choose K}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To calculate the the odds of selecting correctly from the &lt;em&gt;FirstPool&lt;/em&gt;, but incorrectly from the &lt;em&gt;SecondPool&lt;/em&gt;, we again modify the equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mathblock&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;{P - 1 \over P}{K \choose B}{N-K \choose K-B} \over {N \choose K}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computationally, we can derive each of the above equations using the powerball_odds function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-python&quot; data-lang=&quot;python&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;powerball_odds&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pmax&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;sd&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&amp;#39;Calcluates the range of odds of drawing X correct balls in a non-powerball or one-powerball style lottery.&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;sd&quot;&gt;    Keyword Arguments:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sd&quot;&gt;    n: The total number of balls in the lottery&amp;#39;s drawing&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sd&quot;&gt;    k: The total number of balls that a player can draw out of the n pool&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sd&quot;&gt;    pmax:(optional): The maximum value if there is a powerball drawn from a seperate pool.        &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;sd&quot;&gt;    &amp;#39;&amp;#39;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;global&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_list&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;global&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_list_PB&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_list_PB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_list&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;m&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ow&quot;&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;range&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;binomial_coefficient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_b&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;binomial_coefficient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;m&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_c&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;binomial_coefficient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;k&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pmax&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;append&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;((&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_b&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_PB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pmax&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_wo_PB&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_d&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pmax&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;/&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;pmax&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_list_PB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;append&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_PB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;append&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_wo_PB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_list&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;odds_list_PB&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The code snippet above if ran arrives at two different outputs. Which are two lists of the odds for each type of ticket combination. If you are running on the associated Jupyter notebook, follow the cleaning steps and you will arrive at the correct DataFrames that resemble the following tables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;table-1-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;table-1-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Table 1&lt;/em&gt;: The output of the odds for the current Powerball Lottery  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;table-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;booktabs&quot;&gt;
          &lt;thead&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;th colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;cmid&quot;&gt;Output 1: N=69 | P=26&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th class=&quot;nocmid&quot;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Number Correct&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;1/Probability&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Prize&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
          &lt;/thead&gt;
          &lt;tbody&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;0+No Powerball&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.53&lt;/td&gt;           &lt;td&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;0+Powerball&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;38.32&lt;/td&gt;          &lt;td&gt;$4.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;1+No Powerball&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3.68&lt;/td&gt;           &lt;td&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;1+Powerball&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;91.98&lt;/td&gt;          &lt;td&gt;$4.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;2+No Powerball&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;28.05&lt;/td&gt;          &lt;td&gt;$7.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;2+Powerball&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;701.33&lt;/td&gt;         &lt;td&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;3+No Powerball&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;579.76&lt;/td&gt;         &lt;td&gt;$7.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;3+Powerball&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;14,494.11&lt;/td&gt;      &lt;td&gt;$100.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4+No Powerball&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;36,525.17&lt;/td&gt;      &lt;td&gt;$100.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4+Powerball&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;913,129.18&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;td&gt;$50,000.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;5+No Powerball&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;11,688,053.52&lt;/td&gt;  &lt;td&gt;$1,000,000&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;5+Powerball&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;292,201,338.00&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;Jackpot&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
          &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prior to October 7th, 2015, the Powerball lottery had the &lt;em&gt;FirstPool&lt;/em&gt; ranging only to 59, and had the &lt;em&gt;SecondPool&lt;/em&gt; ranging to 35. The output will allow you to visualize how the change in pool sizes changed the odds of the game and has helped to produce several enormous Powerball payouts!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;table-1-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot;&gt; ⊕&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;table-1-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;marginnote&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Table 2&lt;/em&gt;: The output of the odds for the system that was in place for the Powerball Lottery from January 15, 2012 – October 3, 2015 &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;table-wrapper&quot;&gt;
&lt;table class=&quot;booktabs&quot;&gt;
          &lt;thead&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;th colspan=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;cmid&quot;&gt;Output 1: N=59 | P=35&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th class=&quot;nocmid&quot;&gt;&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Number Correct&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;1/Probability&lt;/th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Prize&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
          &lt;/thead&gt;
          &lt;tbody&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;0+No Powerball&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;1.63&lt;/td&gt;           &lt;td&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;0+Powerball&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;55.41&lt;/td&gt;          &lt;td&gt;$4.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;1+No Powerball&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;3.26&lt;/td&gt;           &lt;td&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;1+Powerball&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;110.81&lt;/td&gt;         &lt;td&gt;$4.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;2+No Powerball&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;20.78&lt;/td&gt;          &lt;td&gt;$0.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;2+Powerball&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;706.43&lt;/td&gt;         &lt;td&gt;$7.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;3+No Powerball&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;360.14&lt;/td&gt;         &lt;td&gt;$7.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;3+Powerball&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;12,244.83&lt;/td&gt;      &lt;td&gt;$100.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4+No Powerball&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;19,087.53&lt;/td&gt;      &lt;td&gt;$100.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;4+Powerball&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;648,975.96&lt;/td&gt;     &lt;td&gt;$10,000.00&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;5+No Powerball&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;5,153,632.65&lt;/td&gt;   &lt;td&gt;$1,000,000&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
            &lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;5+Powerball&lt;/td&gt;    &lt;td&gt;175,223,510.00&lt;/td&gt; &lt;td&gt;Jackpot&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
          &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-quick-comparison-between-the-to-tables&quot;&gt;A Quick Comparison between the to tables&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When running through the associated Jupyter notebook we see that the Powerball’s change in pool size accomplished two things. It first improved the odds of having a winning ticket with the Powerball for tickets with 3 correct numbers or less. Secondly it decreased the odds of having a winning ticket with the Powerball for tickets with 4 or more correct numbers. For tickets without the correct Powerball the odds of winning either stayed the same or increased. This change has allowed the Powerball to increase the coverage of the lottery thus implicitly causing higher jackpot payouts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article covered how to use enumerative combinatorics to calculate the different number of combinations for each of the two pools in the Powerball Lottery, and how to calculate the different odds of winning for each type of ticket. Understanding the mathematics lays the foundation for the next article in Powerball series. Within that next article we will learn how to build a web scraper that gathers historical Powerball lottery data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;about-the-author&quot;&gt;About the author&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My name is Jeremy A. Seibert. I built the &lt;strong&gt;Urban Scientist&lt;/strong&gt; as a site to host my explorations in the intersection between Economics and Data Science. Most of the posts that I write will have an associated Jupyter notebook accompanying them feel free to check those out at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/UrbanScientist&quot;&gt;Urban Scientist Github &lt;/a&gt;. Check out the about page for more info on my background.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 27 Dec 2018 02:41:00 -0600</pubDate>
        <link>/articles/18/Mathematics-of-the-Powerball-blog</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">/articles/18/Mathematics-of-the-Powerball-blog</guid>
        
        
        <category>mathematics</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
